Hello everyone and
welcome to EnglishPod.
My name is Marco. My
name is Catherine and it's
the holiday season Marco.
People are eating large
meals with their families
and I think oftentimes
when you cook a lot of
food you have something
extra at the end.
What do we call that?
That's right. Today
we're going to talk about
leftovers, leftovers.
That's the extra food
after your meal that you
eat later maybe the next day.
Exactly. So you know
during Christmas or
during some holidays
we cook so much food that
obviously we can't eat
it all. So we put it back
in the refrigerator
and then we eat it later.
So those are called
leftovers. All right so let's
listen to this dialogue
about leftovers and we'll
be back in a moment to
discuss what's happening
in the dialogue. What's
for dinner? Leftovers.
What? Leftovers of
what and from when?
From last night I took
the leftover turkey,
mixed it with some diced
peppers and onions just
add a little bit of mayonnaise
and made some sandwiches.
Isn't that dangerous though?
I mean bacteria and germs
reproducing on food that was
left out or reheated?
Well I didn't leave the
turkey out of room
temperature for more than an
hour and I refrigerated
soon after we finished eating.
Also in reheating I put in the oven
for 15 minutes at 100 degrees Celsius.
Oh well okay I'm just afraid
of getting food poisoning.
Don't worry about it making a new
meal out of leftovers is almost an art.
Not only do you save money
but you also get to be creative
and have something
different to eat.
All right so a lot of vocab
there let's take a look at it
in language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
All right so Marco there's
one cooking term really in this
dialogue that is it's a
little bit different from
the other so let's start
with that. It's diced.
That's right we were
talking about taking some
peppers or diced
peppers. So when you dice
a vegetable or anything
that you're cooking basically
you're making little little
pieces little squares almost.
That's right so you can cut
something many different ways.
You can cut big pieces and small pieces
but diced peppers. Diced is a specific
way to cut something
in small like you say
small squares and so
in recipes you will often
see this instruction.
Dice the peppers or in this
case the peppers are
diced. That's right all
right so we took some
turkey mixed it with diced
peppers and a lot of things
and the roommate was
a little bit concerned
about bacteria and germs.
All right so bacteria and
germs these sound like
very scientific words.
Bacteria is something
that grows on well
everything really but if you
leave food out for
example it gets bacteria or
germs are things
that can make you sick.
That's right. And so we need
to avoid these things in the
kitchen because they
make us unhealthy and that's
why we wash our hands
and things like that but
when you have food that's
left out the risk is what Marco?
Is that you get
bacteria or germs on it
yeah so it's dangerous
like especially with meat
to leave it out it's very
very dangerous because
you can get some bacteria
that will make you sick
and the reason why
we're a little bit concerned
is especially with meats
is if you leave it out
after cooking it at room
temperature. All right so
room temperature is the
temperature of a normal
room maybe it's 65 degrees
or in what's 25 degrees
Celsius yeah it's the
temperature of the inside of
a room and so it's not
cold it's not hot it's just
normal and when we
leave food out especially
meat like you're saying
we have to be careful you
can't leave it out for
very long if it's something
like eggs or milk or
what we call perishable.
That's right so actually
here comes the other two
words that are a little
bit of a contrast we're
going to talk about food
that is reheated or refrigerated.
All right so the
roommate is explaining
don't worry we have
done these things to this
food so it's safe so
one thing you can do to
food to make it safe
to kill germs is to reheat
it that means well you
know the word heated
right it's to to make
something hot but how
is that different reheated?
Well because you
cooked it already so it
was warm now it went a
little bit cold because
it's at room temperature
so in order to make
sure that it's safe to eat
and you kill that bacteria
you reheat it so you
kind of cook it again a
little bit yeah you cook
it again so with leftovers
we often have to reheat
things because they were
hot then they were cold
and now we want them
hot again so we reheat them
the opposite of that would be refrigerate.
Right and this is what you should do if you
take something and put
it in the refrigerator what
you are doing the verb
the action is to refrigerate
it that's right so to
refrigerate something means
to make it cold you
know there are important
things that we refrigerate
we refrigerate eggs we
refrigerate milk we
refrigerate butter these are
things that can make us sick
if we don't make them cold.
Exactly so those are
the two words now
obviously we it's a little
bit different because
the prefix to reheat
means to do it again
while to refrigerate means
you're just making it cold.
Yeah well there are
important terms and again
we also have the
adjectives this is reheated
or refrigerated but there
are another couple of
phrases that are really
important so let's take
a listen to those
in fluency builder.
Fluency builder. All right so
the first phrase we're going
to take a look at is when
one of the roommates
says hey what's for
dinner? What's for dinner?
All right this is a very
very standard phrase this is
something you'll hear
at home you'll hear with
your friends it's usually
something we say that
when someone is
cooking food for dinner.
That's right we're asking what
are we going to eat for dinner?
Mom what's for a dinner?
Exactly I used to say
that every single day when
I came home from school.
Well obviously you don't
want to say the long phrase
what are we going to
have for dinner tonight so
you just say what's for
dinner? What's for dinner?
What's for dinner? And
then the answer would be
lasagna or turkey
sandwiches. Right exactly.
Now when they started
talking about the leftover
turkey he was a little
bit concerned as we said
about bacteria in germs
because it usually happens
that you get this on
food that was left out.
All right so the verb here is to
leave out to leave something out.
It means to leave something or put
something at room temperature. Right.
So Marco you and I are eating
turkey it's Thanksgiving and
we start to have coffee
and dessert and the turkey
is still in the room. Right.
At room temperature we
did not refrigerate it.
That means it was left out.
How long was it left out?
Well maybe two hours.
Right. Okay that means
so it's not in a refrigerator.
That's right that's
exactly what it means so
maybe you go to sleep
and you left the turkey out
it's still on the table
maybe at room temperature.
Oh no we can't eat it
if we left it out for like
12 hours. Exactly. All
right so it's not good to
leave food out and now
what happens is if you do
eat food that was left
out for too long you could
get food poisoning. Now
this is very serious and
it's something that you
should be very careful
about when you're
cooking. Food poisoning is
getting sick from
your food. Right.
There are different kinds of food poisoning
but usually it makes you throw up.
It makes your stomach hurt.
It's quite painful. That's
right. And so this is why we say
you know you should wash
your hands before you cook.
You should make sure
that you refrigerate meat
because you want to
avoid food poisoning.
That's right and it comes
from the noun poison a poison
which is something that
is harmful for your body.
That's right there are many
different kinds of poison.
But food poisoning
means becoming sick
your body getting sick
after you eat something bad.
That's right. All right
so a lot of great stuff
here we can review
everything one last time.
What's for dinner?
Leftovers. What?
Leftovers of what and
from when? From last night
I took the leftover turkey.
Mix it with some diced
peppers and onions. Add
a little bit of mayonnaise
and made some sandwiches.
Isn't that dangerous though?
I mean bacteria and germs reproducing
on food that was left out or reheated?
Well I didn't leave the turkey
out of room temperature
for more than an hour
and I refrigerated soon
after we finished eating.
Also in reheating I put
in the oven for 15 minutes
at 100 degrees Celsius.
Well okay. I'm just afraid
of getting food poisoning.
Don't worry about it.
Making a new meal out of
leftover is almost an art.
Not only do you save money
but you also get to be creative
and have something different to eat.
All right so this is
actually a good advice
about leftovers, about
having something to eat
but at the same time I
don't know how many people
actually are very
careful with these things.
For example pizza.
Sometimes you leave pizza out
on the table all night
and the next morning you
have some pizza. I
always refrigerate my pizza.
Really? I know people
who leave their pizza out
and then eat it but
there's cheese and sausage
and you know you want
to refrigerate that stuff.
So I always wrap it in
plastic and put it on a
plate in the fridge. Okay
you wrap it in plastic.
Well because in the
refrigerator there's also
germs so you need to make
sure you cover your food.
Right right right and
what about have you ever
had a bad case of food
poisoning because of
having leftovers? No I've
had food poisoning but
not because of leftovers
because as I said before
you know I wrap things I
put them in their refrigerator.
I'm very careful because
I don't want to get
sick or I don't want to
get other people sick
because you know
Thanksgiving or Christmas
you have to give food
to many other people
and you know I don't
want to make anyone sick.
And actually you can't
get food poisoning not
only from leftovers but
from maybe food that
maybe was expired like
sometimes cheese maybe can
be expired and realize it and
you know you get food poisoning.
Or from people who are cooking
with things that are not clean.
So you have something that's
not clean or food that's not fresh
and it makes you very
sick that's food poisoning.
That's right. So it's
an interesting thing
especially with like I said
so many holidays where
you cook so much food
that people have a lot of
leftovers and not only
that but even at restaurants
maybe you order too much
so you have leftovers you
want to take home to
your dog or to have later.
I love leftovers. Let us know.
Do you have leftovers in your
country? Are there things that you
should and shouldn't do with
when cooking? Let us know or our
website is EnglishPod.com.
Alright we'll see you guys there.